Alfred Vincent Kidder Papers 1920-1962 Mss.B.K53
American Philosophical Society
Alfred Vincent Kidder Papers
1920-1962
Mss.B.K53
American Philosophical Society
0.25 Linear feet
Head of the Historical Division of the Carnegie Institution, the archaeologist Alfred V. Kidder specialized in the cliff dwelling cultures of the American Southwest, and is best remembered for work at Pueblo Bonito, Chaco Canyon, and Pecos del Arroyo. Primarily personal in nature, the exchange of letters between Kidder and his colleague and friend Neil M. Judd provides some details on their work on the archaeology of the Southwest. The 68 letters include sporadic references to excavations at Pueblo Bonito, Chaco Canyon, and other archaeological sites, with a few references to other archaeologists and anthropologists.
Kidder, Alfred Vincent, 1885-1963
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Gift of Neil Merton Judd, January 1965.
Scope and Contents note
Primarily personal in nature, the exchange of letters between the archaeologist Alfred V. Kidder and his colleague and friend Neil M. Judd provides some details on their work on the archaeology of the Southwest. The 68 letters include sporadic references to excavations at Pueblo Bonito, Chaco Canyon, and other archaeological sites, with a few references to other archaeologists and anthropologists. The later letters contain some information about Kidder's family.
Biographical/Historical note
Born in the Upper Peninsula of Michigan on October 25, 1885, Alfred V. Kidder enjoyed an outstanding education. As a student at elite prep schools in Cambridge and Boston, Mass., and Switzerland, he entered Harvard, where a childhood interest in Indians blossomed into a profession when he was introduced to the formal study of anthropology. After receiving his bachelors in 1908, he became one of the first Americans to receive a doctorate in archaeology in 1914, working on the pottery of the Southwest.
Working at the Phillips Academy, Andover, until 1929 (primarily on the site at Pecos dekl Arroyo), and thereafter as Chair of the Division of Historical Research of the Carnegie Institution, Kidder's interests remained centered on the Southwest. In addition to the Pecos site in New Mexico, he made valuable contributions to the archaeology of Mesoamerica through the Carnegie, coordinating excavations of Mayan sites at Chichen Itza and Uaxactun in Yucatan and Kaminaljuya in Guatemala. Although he was often denigrated by critics in the profession for being too little concerned with synthesizing the abundant data he collected in the field and for reaching too limited conclusions, many of his conclusions on the classification of southwestern basketry, for instance, endured for many years. He was elected to the American Philosophical Society in 1934, and the American Anthropological Association named an award for eminence in New World archaeology in his honor in the early 1950s.
Kidder retired from the Carnegie in 1950, teaching briefly at the University of California before retiring to his home in Cambridge. He died on June 11, 1963, leaving behind his wife, Madeleine, whom he married in 1910, and five children.
Boas, Franz, 1858-1942; Judd, Neil Merton, 1887-1976; Morley, Sylvanus Griswold, 1883-1948; Archaeology; Chaco Canyon (N.M.)--Antiquities; Indians of North America--Southwest, New; Pueblo Bonito (N.M.)--Antiquities; Southwest, New--Antiquities
- Alfred Vincent Kidder Papers, 1920-1962; 0.25 lin. feet (Box 1)
  - ALS to Neil Merton Judd, July 6, 1920; 1p.; Kidder, Alfred Vincent, 1885-1963
  - ALS to Neil Merton Judd, August 24, 1920; 1p.; Kidder, Alfred Vincent, 1885-1963
    Scope and Contents note
    Believes Chaco will be the biggest thing in American archaeology.
  - ALS to Neil Merton Judd, September 18, 1920; 3p.; Kidder, Alfred Vincent, 1885-1963
    Chaco Canyon excavation.
  - ALS to Neil Merton Judd, September 18, 1920; 5p.; Kidder, Alfred Vincent, 1885-1963
    More on the Chaco dig. National Geographic's involvement gives it profile. Chaco ruins mark the high water mark of southwestern civilizations.
  - ALS to Neil Merton Judd, December 6, 1920; 1p.; Kidder, Alfred Vincent, 1885-1963
  - ALS to Neil Merton Judd, March 29, 1921; 2p.; Kidder, Alfred Vincent, 1885-1963
  - ALS to Neil Merton Judd, March 29, 1921; 2p.; Kidder, Alfred Vincent, 1885-1963
  - TLS Cy to Alfred Vincent Kidder, July 19, 1921; 1p.; Judd, Neil Merton, 1887-1976
    Have excavated the central kiva at Pueblo Bonito.
  - TLS Cy to Alfred Vincent Kidder, July 12, 1922; 1p.; Judd, Neil Merton, 1887-1976
    Pueblo Bonito
  - TLS to Neil Merton Judd, February 18, 1929; 1p.; Kidder, Alfred Vincent, 1885-1963
  - TLS Cy to Alfred Vincent Kidder, March 11, 1933; 1p.; Judd, Neil Merton, 1887-1976
  - TLS to Neil Merton Judd, March 14, 1933; 1p.; Kidder, Alfred Vincent, 1885-1963
  - TLS to Neil Merton Judd, May 15, 1933; 1p.; Kidder, Alfred Vincent, 1885-1963
  - TLS to Neil Merton Judd, May 31, 1933; 1p.; Kidder, Alfred Vincent, 1885-1963
  - TLS to Neil Merton Judd, July 15, 1937; 1p.; Kidder, Alfred Vincent, 1885-1963
  - TLS Cy to Alfred Vincent Kidder, July 21, 1937; 1p.; Judd, Neil Merton, 1887-1976
    Re: photos of Chaco and Pueblo Bonito.
  - TLS to Neil Merton Judd, July 1, 1947; 1p.; Kidder, Alfred Vincent, 1885-1963
  - TLS Cy to Alfred Vincent Kidder, August 14, 1947; 1p.; Judd, Neil Merton, 1887-1976
  - TLS to Neil Merton Judd, August 22, 1947; 1p.; Kidder, Alfred Vincent, 1885-1963
  - TLS to Neil Merton Judd, December 22, 1949; 1p.; Kidder, Alfred Vincent, 1885-1963
  - TLS to Neil Merton Judd, March 17, 1950; 2p.; Alfred V. Kidder Award Committee.
  - TLS to Neil Merton Judd, October 11, 1950; 2p.; Alfred V. Kidder Award Committee.
  - TLS Cy to Alfred Vincent Kidder, October 31, 1950; 1p.; Judd, Neil Merton, 1887-1976
  - TLS to Neil Merton Judd, November 6, 1950; 1p.; Kidder, Alfred Vincent, 1885-1963
  - TLS, March 10, 1951; 1p.; Alfred V. Kidder Award Committee.
  - ALS to Neil Merton Judd, December 10, 1953; 2p.; Kidder, Alfred Vincent, 1885-1963
  - ALS to Neil Merton Judd, January 20, 1954; 2p.; Kidder, Alfred Vincent, 1885-1963
  - ALS to Neil Merton Judd, November 7, 1954; 3p.; Kidder, Alfred Vincent, 1885-1963
    "Boaz's enormous reputation, I've always felt, was to a considerable extent built up by a large and persistent claque (if that's how its spelled -- anyhow, mostly Jewish females)." Vannevar Bush raising Cain; suspects the Carnegie Institution is out of the humanities for good.
  - TLS to Madeleine and Alfred Vincent Kidder, December 26, 1954; 1p.; Judd, Neil Merton, 1887-1976
  - TLS to Neil Merton Judd, June 15, 1955; 1p.; Kidder, Alfred Vincent, 1885-1963
  - TLS Cy to Alfred Vincent Kidder, June 21, 1955; 1p.; Judd, Neil Merton, 1887-1976
  - ALS to Neil Merton Judd, June 24, 1955; 1p.; Kidder, Alfred Vincent, 1885-1963
  - ALS to Neil Merton Judd, November 4, 1955; 2p.; Kidder, Alfred Vincent, 1885-1963
  - TLS to Neil Merton Judd, March 16, 1956; 1p.; Kidder, Alfred Vincent, 1885-1963
  - TLS to Neil Merton Judd, March 30, 1956; 1p.; Kidder, Alfred Vincent, 1885-1963
  - TLS to Neil Merton Judd, September 17, 1956; 1p.; Kidder, Alfred Vincent, 1885-1963
  - TLS Cy to Alfred Vincent Kidder, September 21, 1956; 1p.; Judd, Neil Merton, 1887-1976
  - TLS to Neil Merton Judd, July 29, 1957; 1p.; Kidder, Alfred Vincent, 1885-1963
    Wooden kivas at Pecos.
  - TLS Cy to Madeleine and Alfred Vincent Kidder, June 15, 1958; 1p.; Judd, Neil Merton, 1887-1976
  - TLS to Neil Merton Judd, June 23, 1958; 1p.; Kidder, Alfred Vincent, 1885-1963
  - TLS Cy to Alfred Vincent Kidder, September 20, 1958; 1p.; Judd, Neil Merton, 1887-1976
  - ALS to Neil Merton Judd, September 25, 1958; 2p.; Kidder, Alfred Vincent, 1885-1963
  - TLS to Neil Merton Judd, June 6, 1959; 1p.; Kidder, Alfred Vincent, 1885-1963
  - TLS Cy to Alfred Vincent Kidder, June 29, 1959; 1p.; Judd, Neil Merton, 1887-1976
  - TLS to Neil Merton Judd, July 16, 1959; 1p.; Kidder, Alfred Vincent, 1885-1963
  - TLS Cy to Alfred Vincent Kidder, July 26, 1959; 1p.; Judd, Neil Merton, 1887-1976
  - TLS to Neil Merton Judd, August 4, 1959; 1p.; Kidder, Alfred Vincent, 1885-1963
  - TLS to Neil Merton Judd, September 5, 1959; 1p.; Kidder, Alfred Vincent, 1885-1963
  - TLS to Neil Merton Judd, December 14, 1959; 1p.; Kidder, Alfred Vincent, 1885-1963
  - TLS to Neil Merton Judd, January 18, 1960; 1p.; Kidder, Alfred Vincent, 1885-1963
  - TLS Cy to Madeleine and Alfred Vincent Kidder, January 20, 1960; 1p.; Judd, Neil Merton, 1887-1976
  - TLS Cy to Madeleine and Alfred Vincent Kidder, January 27, 1960; 1p.; Judd, Neil Merton, 1887-1976
  - ALS to Neil Merton Judd, February 12, 1960; 1p.; Kidder, Alfred Vincent, 1885-1963
  - TLS Cy to Alfred Vincent Kidder, February 22, 1960; 1p.; Judd, Neil Merton, 1887-1976
  - TLS Cy to Alfred Vincent Kidder, April 28, 1960; 1p.; Judd, Neil Merton, 1887-1976
  - TLS Cy to Alfred Vincent Kidder, September 16, 1960; 1p.; Judd, Neil Merton, 1887-1976
  - TLS to Alfred Vincent Kidder, July 19, 1921; 1p.; Judd, Neil Merton, 1887-1976
  - TLS to Neil Merton Judd, September 23, 1960; 2p.; Kidder, Alfred Vincent, 1885-1963
  - TLS to Neil Merton Judd, February 26, 1961; 1p.; Kidder, Alfred Vincent, 1885-1963
  - TLS to Neil Merton Judd, May 3, 1961; 1p.; Kidder, Alfred Vincent, 1885-1963
  - TLS to Neil Merton Judd, May 31, 1961; 1p.; Kidder, Alfred Vincent, 1885-1963
  - TLS Cy to Alfred Vincent Kidder, November 8, 1961; 1p.; Judd, Neil Merton, 1887-1976
  - TLS to Neil Merton Judd, November 15, 1961; 2p.; Kidder, Alfred Vincent, 1885-1963
  - TLS to Neil Merton Judd, November 27, 1961; 1p.; Kidder, Alfred Vincent, 1885-1963
  - TLS to Neil Merton Judd, December 6, 1961; 2p.; Kidder, Alfred Vincent, 1885-1963
  - TLS to Neil Merton Judd, January 3, 1962; 1p.; Kidder, Alfred Vincent, 1885-1963
  - TLS Cy to Alfred Vincent Kidder, January 19, 1962; 1p.; Judd, Neil Merton, 1887-1976
  - TLS to Neil Merton Judd, February 6, 1962; 2p.; Kidder, Alfred Vincent, 1885-1963
  - TLS to Neil Merton Judd, February 21, 1962; 1p.; Kidder, Alfred Vincent, 1885-1963
  - TLS Cy to Madeleine and Alfred Vincent Kidder, March 10, 1962; 1p.; Judd, Neil Merton, 1887-1976